Guide to the National Youth Administration Records 1935-1944
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
National Youth Administration Records
1935-1944
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Archives 231
State College of Washington
1 Linear feet of shelf space 2 boxes
Established in 1937, the National Youth Administration was a New Deal program dealing with the effects of the Great Depression. Among other things, it provided grants to college students in exchange for work. The collection consists primarily of records and papers relating to the Pullman campus of WSC's administration of National Youth Administration projects.
Established in 1937, the National Youth Administration was a New Deal program dealing with the effects of the Great Depression. Among other things, it provided grants to college students in exchange for work. The National Youth Administration was closed in 1943.
The collection consists primarily of records and papers relating to the Pullman campus of WSC's administration of National Youth Administration projects. Papers range from summary level program documents to sheets on individual projects (jobs). Most of the papers come from 1936-1939 and from 1941-1943.
The collection is organized in two series. The first series is in subject order, and consists of administrative materials, correspondence, documents, and budgets relating to the implementation of the National Youth Administration on campus in Pullman. The second series consists of individual project statements. Series two is then broken into two subseries, the first being statements from 1936-1938, organized alphabetically by sponsoring department. The second series comprises the last two folders, and is project statements from 1942-1943, alphabetically by department in two folders maintaining their original separation as active and inactive projects, and including some administrative materials relating to the overseeing of those projects.
This collection is open and available for research use.
These records were transferred to Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections sometime prior to 1984, from an unknown donor, and designated as W049. The collection was preliminarily processed ca. 1984, but was not completed and no finding aid was created.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
United States. National Youth Administration.; Washington State University.; State College of Washington.; United States. National Youth Administration.; Washington State University.
College students -- Employment -- United States.; New Deal, 1933-1939 -- Washington (State).; Public works -- Washington (State).; Youth -- Employment -- Washington (State).; Student aid -- Washington (State).
Washington (State); Colleges and Universities; Public Works; Student Life
- Series 1: Administrative Materials and other documents
    - Annual Report, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Annual Report, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Annual Report, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Assistance Forms, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Circulars, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Equipment and Material Inventory, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Federal Student Aid Organization, Procedure Results, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Manual: Official Procedure for School Year 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Manual: The National Youth Administration Central Office, Pullman, Washington, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Manual of Student Work Procedure, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Payrolls for N.Y.A. 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Payroll Master List, 2nd Semester, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Payroll Master List, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Projects to be Considered by Committee (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Work Plan, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Work Plan (Proposed), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series 2: Project (Job) Statements
  - Subseries 2.1: 1936-1938
    - Agricultural Education (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Agricultural Engineering (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Agricultural Experimental Station (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Agronomy-Soils (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Architectural Engineering (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Alumni (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Animal Husbandry (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Agronomy (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Associated Students (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Bacteriology (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Botany (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Buildings and Grounds (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Bursar (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Business Administration (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Campus (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Chemistry (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Civil Engineering (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - College Farm (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Dairy Husbandry (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Dean of Men (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Dean of Women (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Education (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Electrical Engineering (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Engineering Experimental Station (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - English (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Extension (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Farm Management (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Fine Arts (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Forestry and Range Management (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Geology (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - History and Political Science (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Home Economics (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Horticulture (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Industrial Arts (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Libraries (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Mathmatics (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Mechanical Engineering (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Military (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Mining and Metalurgy (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Music (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - National Youth Administration (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Pharmacy (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Photo Studio (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Physical Education (Women and Men) (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Physics (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Plant Pathology (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Poultry (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Psychology (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Public Health Committee (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Pullman Chamber of Commerce (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Pullman, City of (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Pullman (Off-Campus) Organizations: Red Cross, Boy Scouts, Kiwanis Club, Camp Fire Girls (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Radio (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Registrar (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Resettlement (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Scholarship Committee (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Sociology and Rural Sociology Research Laboratory (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Speech (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - U.S. Geological Survey (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Vetrinary Medicine (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Washington School of Religion (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Washington State Highway Dept. (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Y.M.C.A. (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Y.W.C.A. (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Zoology (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Subseries 2.2: 1942-1943
    - Active (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Inactive (Box 2, Folder 85)